<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="lillet"
         xml:id="guide.users.concepts.stability">
 <info><title>Package stability</title></info>

 <para>
  Versioning and stability are separate entities for
  <link linkend="guide.users.concepts.package">packages</link>.
  The stability of a package determines how likely the package is to contain bugs
  or to have changes to its <link linkend="guide.users.concepts.api">API</link>.
  A distinction is made between the version/stability of the API and the
  version/stability of the code.
 </para>
 <para>
  This simple chart shows the meaning of a package's stability:
  <table>
   <title>What a package's stability means</title>
   <tgroup cols="3">
    <thead>
     <row>
      <entry>Stability type</entry>
      <entry>Stability</entry>
      <entry>Description</entry>
     </row>
    </thead>

    <tbody>
     <row>
      <entry>Release</entry>
      <entry><literal>devel</literal></entry>
      <entry>
       The package is under development and will change dramatically, both
       adding new features, changing the design, and fixing many bugs.  It may
       not function at all and be more of a proof-of-concept.  There may be
       little to no documentation or unit tests.  Use at your own risk.
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>Release</entry>
      <entry><literal>alpha</literal></entry>
      <entry>
       The package is ready for testing by hard core users.  Features are
       still being developed, but the program should work.  Subsequent releases
       may have major changes.
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>Release</entry>
      <entry><literal>beta</literal></entry>
      <entry>
       The package is nearly ready for public release and usage in production.
       Documentation is complete, unit tests are complete, and the API is
       frozen (will not change) unless major problems are found.
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>Release</entry>
      <entry><literal>stable</literal></entry>
      <entry>
       The package is ready for use in production.
       Documentation is complete, unit tests are complete, and the API is
       frozen completely and will not change.
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>API</entry>
      <entry><literal>devel</literal></entry>
      <entry>
       The API will change dramatically between releases, and cannot be relied upon.
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>API</entry>
      <entry><literal>alpha</literal></entry>
      <entry>
       The API is starting to stabilize, but may still have major changes.
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>API</entry>
      <entry><literal>beta</literal></entry>
      <entry>
       The API will only have changes if major bugs are found.
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>API</entry>
      <entry><literal>stable</literal></entry>
      <entry>
       The API will not change and can be relied upon.
      </entry>
     </row>
    </tbody>
   </tgroup>
  </table>
 </para>
 <section xml:id="guide.users.concepts.stability.conventions">
  <para>
   There are a few conventions that should be followed when deciding which
   stability to use for your package.  In general, the API stability should be
   equal to or better than the release stability.
  </para>
  <para>
   Here is a helpful chart of stabilities:
   <table>
    <title>Which stability to use</title>
    <tgroup cols="3">
     <thead>
      <row>
       <entry>Release Stability</entry>
       <entry>API Stability</entry>
       <entry>Scenario</entry>
      </row>
     </thead>
 
     <tbody>
      <row>
       <entry><literal>devel</literal></entry>
       <entry><literal>devel</literal></entry>
       <entry>
        This package is brand new, no documentation, no tests, more of
        a proof-of-concept.  It may not work at all.
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry><literal>alpha</literal></entry>
       <entry><literal>alpha</literal></entry>
       <entry>
        This package has been developed extensively, and is ready for testing
        by the outside world, has some documentation or full documentation
        and tests, but the API or design is subject to dramatic change if
        necessary.  Bugs are likely
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry><literal>alpha</literal></entry>
       <entry><literal>beta</literal></entry>
       <entry>
        This package has a relatively certain API, but may contain bugs, and
        the API may change, but most changes will be small.
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry><literal>beta</literal></entry>
       <entry><literal>beta</literal></entry>
       <entry>
        This package is approaching release, the code is stabilizing as well as
        the API
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry><literal>beta</literal></entry>
       <entry><literal>stable</literal></entry>
       <entry>
        This package is in the release candidate stage, has full documentation
        and tests, as well as a frozen API.  Bugs may still be present in the
        code.
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry><literal>stable</literal></entry>
       <entry><literal>stable</literal></entry>
       <entry>
        This package is ready for use in production, has full documentation
        and tests, and the API can be relied upon as frozen.
       </entry>
      </row>
     </tbody>
    </tgroup>
   </table>
  </para>
 </section>
</section>
