<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<refentry xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="lillet" xml:id="core.pear.system.intro">
   <refnamediv>
    <refname>Introduction</refname>
    <refpurpose>General usage informations</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>

  <refsection xml:id="core.pear.system.intro.clistyle"><info><title>Command line style</title></info>
     
    <para>
     The <classname>System</classname> functions are called like there
     commandline pendants
     <programlisting role="php">
   <![CDATA[
if (!System::rm('-r file1 dir1')) {
	print "Could not delete all the files";
}
   ]]>
     </programlisting>
     The arguments of the functions can be introduced as string or array:
    <programlisting role="php">
	System::rm(array('-r', 'file1', 'dir1'));
    </programlisting>
	System works like any other PHP function and will return
	<parameter>FALSE</parameter>,
	when the operation could not be completed entirely or partially. System
	won't stop when a error is found, it will try to continue. For example,
	if you are trying to delete three files and the first one can't be deleted,
	the next two files will be deleted but the function will return
	<parameter>FALSE</parameter>.
    </para>
	<para>
  Errors will be printed out using the PHP function 
  <function>trigger_error()</function> so all
	the System methods can be silenced prefix a '@' sign before the function
 call (for example: <command>@System::mkdir('-p dir1/dir2/dir3');</command>).
	</para>

  </refsection>
  <refsection xml:id="core.pear.system.intro.compatibility"><info><title>Compatibility</title></info>
    
    <para>
     <classname>System</classname> provides file system functions.
     They are named like the file system commands on Unix systems
     and supports the same options <emphasis>independent</emphasis>
     of your operation system.
    </para>
    <para>
     At the moment the functions are tested under Linux and Windows. Further
     reports about compatibility on other systems are welcome.
    </para>
    <warning>
     <para>
      In earlier versions of PHP 4, <function>unlink</function> may fail
      on Windows. This bug is already fixed in up-to-date versions.
     </para>
    </warning>
   </refsection>

   <refsection xml:id="core.pear.system.intro.manpages"><info><title>Man Pages</title></info>
    
    <para>
     This manual describes the parameters of the <classname>System</classname>
     functions, most only a string. The arguments and options of the specific
     command are <emphasis>not</emphasis> documented in the manual. Please take
     a look on the man-pages on unix-like systems
     <programlisting>
     <command>man</command> <parameter>commandname</parameter>
     </programlisting>
     or when man-pages not available on your system, visit the
     <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="&url.man.index;">On-line UNIX manual pages</link>
    </para>
   </refsection>

  </refentry>
