<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="lillet" xml:id="installationpyrus.introduction">
    <info><title>Introduction: it's simple</title></info>

   <para>
    Installing Pyrus is much simpler than installing PEAR.  Installing PEAR
    requires downloading a separate installation and installing PEAR before you
    can use it to install any packages.
   </para>
   <para>
    To install pyrus, you must follow two simple steps:
    <orderedlist>
     <listitem>
      <simpara>
       Install PHP 5.3.1 or newer.  Pyrus needs the phar, simplexml, libxml2,
       spl and pcre extensions in order to work.  Fortunately, these are all
       enabled by default in PHP 5.3.
      </simpara>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <simpara>
       download pyrus.phar from the pear2.php.net website front page
      </simpara>
     </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    That's it, pyrus has no external dependencies.  Using Pyrus is also simple,
    one simply passes it to the command-line interface (CLI) like so:
   </para>
   <para>
    <screen>
     <![CDATA[
php pyrus.phar install packagename
     ]]>
    </screen>
   </para>
   <para>
    The first time pyrus is run on your system, it will ask where you would like
    to install packages.  After this, one can simply use it.
   </para>
   <para>
    To match PEAR, it is also possible to create a convenience script for
    accessing pyrus.  Here is a sample script for unix systems:
   </para>
   <para>
    <programlisting role="script">
     <![CDATA[
#!/bin/bash
/usr/local/bin/php -dphar.readonly=0 /home/username/pyrus.phar $*
     ]]>
    </programlisting>
   </para>
   <para>
    If your system has open_basedir enabled, the script should instead look like:
   </para>
   <para>
    <programlisting role="script">
     <![CDATA[
#!/bin/bash
/usr/local/bin/php -dphar.readonly=0 -dopen_basedir= -dsafe_mode= /home/username/pyrus.phar $*
     ]]>
    </programlisting>
   </para>
   <para>
    Windows users can create a batch file similar to the unix script named pyrus.bat:
   </para>
   <para>
    <programlisting role="script">
     <![CDATA[
@ECHO OFF
C:\php5\php -dphar.readonly=0 -dopen_basedir= -dsafe_mode= C:\php5\pyrus.phar %*
     ]]>
    </programlisting>
   </para>
   <para>
    Place the shell script (on unix) or batch file (on windows) in your path,
    and then you can run commands like so:
   </para>
   <para>
    <screen>
     <![CDATA[
pyrus install packagename
     ]]>
    </screen>
   </para>
  </section>
